Now let's go back and talk about four loops and range and numerate and then we'll
come back to the last part of this exercise afterwards.
So we are talking about loops.
Loops in Python don't necessarily look like they do in other programming languages.
If you write JavaScript, Java, or some other languages, you might be used to loops that
look something like this where you define a four, you define a starting point, you define
what number you're looping two, and then define a condition that helps progress that
starting value to the ending condition.
Looping in Python is a lot simpler and cleaner and actually a lot of other programming
languages have borrowed from Python syntax and now incorporates some of these nicer
looping structures.
So in the past we had used this in keyword to test if an item was inside of a sequence,
but when we combine the in keyword with the four keyword, in can be used to indicate that
you are looping over each item in a sequence.
So this syntax for this is for a single item and that's going to be a temporary variable
name in items which is a sequence followed by a colon, you're going to start a new line
and then in-dent under to loop in that four loop.
And again if you're in the repule, you'll need to press enter again in order to see the
results.
Instead, I'm going to make a new Python file called loop.py and we can start up here.
So if I run, if I exit my repule here and I run this Python file in the terminal, I
will see the color is red, green, blue, and orange.
And I'm printing out the value of color, which I define right here inside of my loop.
Something interesting that I want to point out is that loops don't have the same scope
as functions.
So here the four loop was updating the value of color, each time that we looped over
the loop, when we are outside of the loop, this variable color still exists.
And the value of that variable is the last value that was in the list.
So something to be mindful of when you're thinking about scope.
There's also a range function that lets you generate a range of numbers.
You can pass in one value into it.
If you want to see what is actually generated, you're going to need to pass this range
into a list because this is what's called a generator type in Python.
Python 2 used to be more inefficient in Python 3.
If you pass a large number in here, it's not going to create a new data structure where
the numbers from 1 to that very large number are all stored in memory at once.
So if you want to take a look at this, let's pass it into the list constructor.
And it would tell you what this would generate all at once.
But generally, because you're going to be using this range to loop over something,
you don't necessarily have to have that whole range in memory.
You only care about what that value is while you're in the loop and what the next
value might be.
And that's an optimization that allows Python to save memory.
You could also pass in two numbers where this would be the starting point and this would
be the ending point, the ending point is not inclusive.
So you can go ahead and use range along with the for loop.
And that will go ahead and print out each item in this range.
Now if you need to get a handle on an index, let's say that I have these colors.
If you need to print out both the name of the color and the position that it was in,
don't go back to your old style for loops.
You don't need to declare a variable to keep track of I and then increment I and then
print that out, there is a shortcut in Python for that called enumerate.
And the enumerate function you pass it in a list or a set and it will return a tuple.
So if we passed in the value of enumerate to look at it,
we'll see that it returns a list of tuples where the first item is zero.
So that's the index and the second item is what was contained in our list.
So this matches a position with a value and then you can use that tuple unpacking that
we saw earlier inside of a for loop in order to get at both of these values at once.
So I can say for index color in enumerate colors.
And then I can print out the index and the color without having to keep track of an
I without incrementing it without creating any extra variables.
The use of the enumerate function is one of those things that differentiates beginners
to Python who don't necessarily understand the core concepts like all of you do with programmers
and Python who are more intermediate.
If I spot somebody using the enumerate function, I know that they have a pretty good
understanding of what's going on under the hood and what Python code looks like.
Now remember if we want to loop over a dictionary, we need to be mindful that by default
a dictionary just gives us back the keys.
So we need to explicitly ask for both keys and values.
So I'm going to grab this dictionary right here with some hex colors.
If I were going to loop over this, I would just get the keys.
If I wanted to loop over keys and values at the same time, I would need to call hexcolors.items
to get back the keys and the values.
And look, this is returning a list of tuples that means that we can use tuple unpacking.
So I can now say 4 key comma value in hexcolors.items print the key print something else
and then print the value.
So this is how I loop over both the key and the value in a dictionary at once and use
tuple unpacking to get the key into a variable named key and the value into a variable
named value so that I could then use them in my loop.
Python also has wild loops and for those you will need to use some sort of counter.
I'm not going to jump into wild loops because you all have some programming experience.
And so I expect that wild loops look pretty similar to what they might in your programming
language of choice.
I will say that these syntax for wild loops looks something like this.
So I can say maybe vowel is equal to 0 and then say while vowel is less than 5, print
the value and then increase the value by 1, either by saying value equals vowel plus 1 or
saying vowel plus equals 1 and that will go ahead and run a wild loop.
So for wild loops you just do wild and an expression that evaluates to true or false.
When you're doing wall loops make sure that you will eventually have a condition where
this is false otherwise your program will run for forever.
If you need to short circuit your loop you can use the return statement to break out
of it.
So let's say I had some names.
If I wanted to loop over these names and stop when I found the target value so I can
say if name is equal to stand oops sorry what I wanted to say was that you would want
to use this in a function.
Let's do this a little bit differently let's say return target and pass in the name of
a target and now we could do the same for loop and make sure that it is indented correctly
oops sorry if name is equal to the target we're going to return the name.
Let me make sure that is indented correctly so now I can return target and it will print
stand or I can make a new target of Nina and once that target is found the function will
return so that's a way of short circuiting a loop a different way of short circuiting
loops is with break and continue.
These are more advanced concepts that I'm not going to cover but there is an optional chapter
here in the course website where you can follow through on those.